Guide to the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington records, 1937-1988 MS2012
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington records
1937-2005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2012
46 Linear Feet
Collection consists primarily of papers and printed matter generated by the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington, including meeting minutes, memoranda, correspondence, reports, and press releases. It also contains a number of photographs and a single audio cassette. The material ranges in date from 1937 to 1988, but the bulk of the material ranges from 1965 to 1979.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The Records of the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington were donated to the Gelman Library in 1986. Additional accessions were accepted in 1988 and 1992, and future accessions are expected.
Historical or Biographical Note
Since 1938, the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington (now the Jewish Community Relations Council of Greater Washington) has served the Jewish community by responding to important issues and speaking out on behalf of the community's concerns. It aims to promote the cultural, social, economic, and philanthropic interests and advance the national and spiritual aspirations of Jewish people.
On March 6, 1938 twenty-five presidents of Jewish organizations in the greater Washington area joined together to consider the formation of a communal council capable of addressing the needs of the Jewish community in an organized and cohesive manner. From this initial meeting evolved the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington, D.C. (It was known as the Jewish Community Council of Washington until the late 1940's). They created the organization to respond to certain immediate social concerns, including the fate of Jews in Nazi Germany, as well as the specter of rising anti-Semitism in the United States. On 31 January 1939, the group held its first formal meeting and 73 representatives from 39 organizations approved a Constitution and By-Laws.
Rabbi Solomon Metz, Hymen Goldman, and Rabbi Isadore Breslau were among the founders of the Council and served in succession as its first three presidents. Their contributions shaped the Council, along with those of Isaac Franck, who from 1948 to 1973 was its Executive Director and its guiding force.
Born in Russia in 1909, Franck came to America as a teenager and studied at New York University, Columbia University, and Harvard University, eventually earning a Ph.D in philosophy from the University of Maryland in 1966.
When Franck arrived in Washington to take over the Council in 1948, there were approximately 60 Jewish organizations participating. When he retired in 1973, there were over 170. During Franck's time the Council grew dramatically and worked with other organizations and faiths to address a wide range of social and political problems. Among these were issues of civil rights and desegregation, education, assistance to the poor, and Home Rule for the District of Columbia.
After Frank's retirement, in the 1970's and 1980's, the concern for the treatment of Soviet Jews and issues of war and peace in Israel and the Middle East occupied much of the Council's agenda.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of papers and printed matter, including meeting minutes, memoranda, correspondence, reports, and press releases. It also contains a number of photographs and a single audio cassette. The material ranges in date from 1937 to 1988, but the bulk of the material ranges from 1965 to 1979.
The Administrative Files series contains documents such as the Constitution and By-Laws of the organization, meeting minutes, and budget reports, which provide a continuous record of the Council from 1938 to 1983. The Committees, Task Forces, and Working Groups series comprises almost half of the total collection, and contains material dealing with the plight of Soviet Jewry, Israel's relationship with countries in the Middle East, and committees formed to address social conditions within the Greater Washington Area. The Other Constituent Organizations series deals with organizations which address many of the same concerns the Council does, and which worked in collaboration with the Council in a number of ways. The Subject Files series covers a wide range of topics ranging from anti-Semitism to the Vietnam War. The Oversized Series contains a small number of materials too large to be kept in their original folders. The series arrangement established by the agency has been maintained, with the exception of moving materials on Isaac Franck from the Subject Files series to the Administrative Files series.
The collection contains significant material on various committees, namely the Executive Committee, the Intergroup Relations Committee, and the Soviet Jewry Committee. It contains less documenting the history of the Council's early years in the late 1930's and 1940's. In addition, with the exception of Isaac Franck, the collection lacks detailed information on the organization's prominent members and presidents.
The Records of the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington were donated to the Gelman Library in 1986. Additional accessions were accepted in 1988 and 1992, and future accessions are expected. The Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington and individuals whose work forms part of this collection retain literary property rights. The main offices of the Council are currently located in Rockville, Maryland. Previously, they were located in downtown Washington, D.C.
Please note: this collection contains unprocessed materials. Ask staff about using this material.
Collection Organization
Organized into six series: Administrative files; Committees, task forces, and working groups; Other constituent organizations; Subject files; Oversized material; and Accession 2007.
Antisemitism; Israel; Committees; Vietnam war; Photographs; Middle East; Jews, Soviet; Washington (D.C.); Audiotapes; Jews; Franck, Isaac; Jewish Community Center of Greater Washington
- Administrative files, 1938-1985; MS2012 Series 1; 6 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series documents the founding and early years of the Council. Topics include: delegate assembly, executive committee, organizational committees, and the Isaac Franck files. The bulk of the collection materials in this series are agendas, memoranda, minutes, lists of delegates/presidents, resolutions, reports, addresses, news releases, newsletters, correspondence, Constitution and By-Laws of the Council, budgets/expenditures, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
  The material in this series is dated from 1938 to 1985, with the bulk spanning the years 1950 to 1975. Isaac Franck is included in this series because as Executive Director of the JCCGW from 1948 to 1973, he was instrumental in shaping its focus and direction in the formative years and beyond. These records are very useful in examining the evolution of the Council's organization, representation, and focus. Of particular interest in this series are the early Constitution and By-Laws. Also of note are the files of Isaac Franck, which include his personal correspondence and writings from 1942 to 1973, among them materials related to his 1957 trip to post-war Germany.
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1973 January-March (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1973 April-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1974 January-April (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1974 May-June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1974 July-December (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1978 January-April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1978 May-December (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Delegate Assembly Records, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1950 January-February (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1950 March-June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1950 September-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1951 January-April (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1951 May-October (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1951 November-December (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1952 January-April (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1952 May-July (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1952 August-October (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1952 November-December (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 January-February (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 February 04 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 March-April (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 May (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 June (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 September (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 October (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1953 November-December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 January-February (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 March (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 April (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 May (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 September-October (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 November (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1954 December (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 January-March (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 April-June (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 September (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 October (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 November (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1955 December (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1956 January-February (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1956 March-June (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1956 September (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1956 October (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1956 November-December (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1957 January-February (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1957 April-June (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1957 September (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1957 October (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1957 November-December (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 January (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 February (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 March (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 April-June (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 September (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 October (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1958 November-December (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1959 February-March (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1959 April-June (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1959 September-October (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1959 November-December (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1960 January-February (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1960 March-April (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1960 May-June (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1960 July-September (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1960 October-December (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1961 January (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1961 February-March (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1961 April-June (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1961 August-October (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1961 November-December (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1962 January-February (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1962 March-April (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1962 May-June (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1962 September-October (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1962 November-December (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 January-February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 March (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 April (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 May-August (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 September-October (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1963 November-December (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1964 January-February (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1964 March-April (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1964 May-June (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1964 September-October (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1964 November-December (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 January (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 February (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 March-April (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 May (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 June (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 September-October (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1965 November-December (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 January-February (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 March (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 April (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 May-June (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 September-October (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1966 November-December (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1967 January-February (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1967 March-May (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1967 September-December (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1968 January-February (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1968 March-April (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1968 May-June (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1968 September-October (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1968 November-December (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 January-February (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 March-April (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 May-June (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 August-September (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 October (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1969 November-December (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1970 January-February (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1970 March-April (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1970 May-June (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1970 September-October (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1970 November-December (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1971 January-April (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1971 May-December (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1972 January-June (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1972 September-December (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 January (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 February (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 March-April (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 May-June (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 September-October (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1973 November-December (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 January-February (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 March (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 April (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 May-June (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 September-October (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1974 November-December (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1975 January-February (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1975 March-May (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1975 June-August (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1975 September-October (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1975 November-December (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1976 January-February (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1976 March-April (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1976 May-July (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1976 September-October (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1976 November-December (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1977 January (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1977 February-March (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1977 April-June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1977 August-October (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1977 November-December (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 January-February (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 March-April (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 May-June (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 July (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 September-October (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1978 November-December (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1979 January-June (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1979 August-December (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1980 January-March (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1980 April-August (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1980 September-December (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1981 January-June (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1981 July-October (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1981 November-December (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1982 January-March (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1982 April-September (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1982 October-December (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1983 January-March (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee Records, 1983 April-June (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1942-1953 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Isaac Franck Files - Germany Trip, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Isaac Franck Files - Germany Trip, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1958-1960 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1964-1967 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Isaac Franck Files - Retirement, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Isaac Franck Files - Retirement, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Isaac Franck Files, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Isaac Franck Files - Death, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Committees, task torces, and working groups, 1941-1983; MS2012 Series 2; 22.5 Linear feet
  This series is comprised of seven separate committees, task forces, and working groups within the Jewish Community Council of Greater Washington over the years. These groups include: bicentennial commission, community task force, holocaust committee, intergroup relations, urban affairs/social action committee, Soviet Jewry, Israel and the Middle East, and miscellaneous committees, task forces. The most prominent among these are the Soviet Jewry and Israel and the Middle East committees. The bulk of the materials comprising this series are reports, budgets, memoranda, correspondence, photographs, booklets, minutes, newsletters, and transcripts. The material in this series is dated from 1941 to 1983, with the bulk of it covering the years from 1968 to 1979. The committees and task forces contained in this series demonstrate the commitment of the local Jewish community to social and political issues both at home and abroad.
  - Bicentennial Commission: Jewish Bicentennial Commission of Greater Washington Jewish Citizens of the Greater Washington Area in support of Bicentennial [includes a list of names], Circa 1976; Series 2 (Map-folder 1)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Jewish Bicentennial Commission of Greater Washington, 1977 October 24 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Jewish Bicentennial Commission of Greater Washington - General Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Jewish Bicentennial Commission of Greater Washington - Memorandum, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Jewish Bicentennial Commission of Greater Washington - New Releases, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Bicentennial Finance Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Bicentennial Jewish Guidebook, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Bicentennial Jewish Guidebook - Drafts, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Bicentennial Tapestry Project, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Bicentennial Commission: Bicentennial Symposium, 1976 November 06-07 (Box 12, Folder 9)